Two of the oldest political parties in
the world are in danger of being
completely wiped out right now in the
UK. Rate of change in the economy goes
down, rate of change in politics can go
way up. Both Labour and the Tories are
on the ropes, especially Labour after
the results of the last election. The
local elections were a complete
bloodbath. A new system is emerging in
the aftermath. But the aftermath of
what? That's the thing. That's where all
of this is coming from. No one is
willing to say what this is truly about.
And that is a huge warning both to
politicians in office as well as the
politicians who would like to be in
office. In the UK, the Tories, the
so-called conservatives, spent the first
part of the 2020s doing the same things
everyone else did. They kept saying they
got the economy on the right track only
to get their butts handed to them in
2024. So Labour came sweeping in, the
so-called liberals, and they promised to
do one thing. That was to fix the
economy right at the moment when the
economy, the globally synchronized
economy, flat beverage, to use that term
as a verb here. And it flat beverage
worse than the UK than almost everywhere
else. Not just affordability,
unemployment, which certainly makes it
far harder to afford anything than it
already had been. The UK is a perfect
illustration of this main symptom, but
it's no longer the only obvious one.
France, for example, just today put out
some shocking unemployment numbers
there, too, as we'll get to. So this is
a warning, a real warning to Nigel
Farage's brand new party as it ascends
toward maybe a majority at some point
and therefore the top role in the
British government. Don't promise to fix
an economy you can't say why it was
broken in the first place or what's
really the biggest symptom to it. This
is exactly what Labour did in 2024 as
the Tories had done up until then, and
it has buried both parties maybe for
good. All over the world we see the same
thing. The guys in office get thrown
out, the new ones come in promising to
fix the economy only to do nothing for
the kitchen table to get thrown out all
over again. It's a warning to
politicians, it's a warning from voters,
it's a warning on the one thing that
truly matters which no one is willing to
say. Because of the stock market and
central bankers, we're supposed to
believe everything is fine when voters
keep telling you rate of change in the
economy goes down, rate of change in
politics can and is going way up.
So last week the UK held local council
elections and the results were simply
historic. There's really no other way to
describe them. Complete wipeout. So for
anyone outside the UK who's watching,
these contests are kind of like for the
United States the US midterms though
it's a very rough analogy. Basically
they're a chance to see where voters are
in between the big national elections.
The last one of those had been held in
2024 which swept the Labour Party back
into the majority in Parliament and Keir
Starmer to the Prime Minister's office
ousting the Tories after more than a
decade. Now Starmer and his comrades won
on an economic message. We're going to
do things differently than the other
guys they said, you know, Rishi Sunak
and Liz Truss and Boris Johnson. We're
going to actually listen to voters who
keep telling us the economy's terrible
and it's not getting any better. This is
the basic setup we've seen all over the
planet time and time again including, if
you recall, in the United States in that
same year 2024. The economy under the
old guys was terrible and getting worse.
We're going to do it very differently.
That's really all they ever say. We'll
do it differently. And to be honest, up
until now that's all they had to say
because that's a better message than
what voters have been getting before
then. Whether the Tories or Joe Biden,
Kamala Harris in the US, they kept
saying the economy's fine, it's good.
It's booming. Or maybe it's improving.
It's not great, but it's improving. Just
look at the stock market. So, this is
already a warning. Voter dissatisfaction
cuts across party lines. During that
same critical year, 2024, the global
pivot, the Brits tossed out the
so-called conservatives to give the
so-called liberals a shot, and the
Americans kicked out the so-called
liberals to give the so-called
conservatives theirs. And it hasn't
worked. So, now both American and
British voters are even angrier.
What is a Eurodollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education, and you want
clarity in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our memberships
scale with your goals. At Eurodollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Eurodollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore, master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence. Click the link in the
description to visit
eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
And the Brits just took out that anger
on Starmer and Labour, but rather than
handing power back to the so-called
conservatives and the Tories, they
pulled the lever in huge historic ways
for a brand new party called Reform UK.
The results were staggering if
unsurprising. Unsurprising in the
respect of actually admitting the
economy, therefore the kitchen table
continues to be the driving force behind
the upheaval. Rate of change in it goes
down, rate of change in politics goes
way up. So just look at the rate of
change for the council elections in the
UK last week. Reform, this brand new
party, picked up 1,451
seats after having just two previously.
From two to 1453.
Now Labour lost nearly 1,500, leaving
them with still over 1,000, and the
Tories, as I said, dropped yet again,
losing another 563,
leaving the party with just 801. Now the
Green Party of the far left also did
well, gaining 441. In other words, big
picture, the two main parties or the two
former main parties lost 2,000
councilors combined, with 1,500 of those
going to Farage and Reform UK, and the
other 500 to the Greens and other left
leaners.
Quote, "Labour are being wiped out by
Reform in many of their most traditional
areas, and what you're going to see
later on today is the Conservative Party
being wiped out in their heartlands."
That's according to Nigel Farage. What
he told reporters Friday morning is some
councils were still counting the votes.
He insisted his upstart party, which won
just five seats in Parliament in
Britain's last general election nearly
two years ago, but has since climbed in
the polls, was no longer a quote "fluke"
or a protest vote, but a truly national
party that was here to stay. "What's
happened is a truly historic shift in
British politics," Farage said. He added
that Reform's broad gains across England
showed that his populist party could
challenge the traditional dominance of
labor and the Conservative Party. It's a
big, big day, not just for our party,
but a complete reshaping of British
politics in every way.
The fact that Reform won in labor
strongholds, as well as conservative
strongholds, is the most critical and
damning piece of evidence here. As the
guy once said, it is the economy,
stupid. And last week's results in the
UK just speak for themselves. A historic
realignment is currently underway as the
old parties continue to pay lip service
to the real problem. Voters are being
left behind. Consumer prices, yes, they
soared ahead in '21 and '22, but incomes
never caught up now 5 years later. And
they keep calling it affordability when
it's simple, basic, kitchen table
economics. And worse for the kitchen and
the table, the politicians who still
don't get it, the lack of income over
the last 5 years has been made a lot
worse by the rise of unemployment that
literally no one wants to talk about.
This is just flat-out astonishing in
country after country. Joblessness is
rising, and it has been for years to the
point some of these official rates on
unemployment are just plain ugly. But
you never hear about it anywhere, which
is an enormous mistake. It's a mistake
for a bunch of different reasons, but
for politics just as much. And the
reason you never hear about
unemployment, and instead only ever hear
some politicians are mentioning
affordability, is simply because
affordability doesn't sound as bad. It
sounds like something that can be
tweaked with just the right mix of a
government policies if you're so kind as
to vote their way. Affordability sounds
like it can be fixed with some tax cuts,
or on the other side, maybe another kind
of government handout, just some policy
fine-tuning. And it is pure If
the prime minister or the president or
whomever told the truth and said
unemployment after incomes getting to be
very serious, how would people react?
Quite differently. First of all, those
politicians currently in office, they
never ever want to use the word
unemployment. Kiss of death. And for
those opposing them, joblessness sounds
a lot less like something a new
political party might be able to fix.
Now, we also have to consider just how
much central bankers play a role in
this, too. Politicians, I mean, look,
they have no idea what's going on in the
economy. So, they're told what to
believe by a group of people who really
don't have any more idea about what's
going on in the economy, and that's
central bankers. I mean, they all have
the fancy degrees, the right pedigree,
the impressive titles, and the flashy
offices. Central bankers look the part,
which, as I'll remind you, is the entire
point, their only point. It's all about
appearances.
And they're all in on inflation and have
been, especially the past year to 14
months. Remember tariff inflation? They
can't sell tariff inflation and now oil
inflation and that therefore the hawkish
policy stance to politicians or the
public when unemployment is running
rampant.
Calling it an affordability crisis makes
it sound more like the inflation no one
has because it might also encompass the
joblessness that everyone increasingly
does. And politicians, as we know, they
will defer to the central bankers when
any truly smart politician would begin
truly challenging them and all their
assumptions, predictions, and forecasts,
and their theories. Start by calling
them out on how they keep downplaying
this economic reality. Or worse, by
saying that rate cuts or lower rates
will somehow fix everything. The
evidence conclusively, conclusively
shows yet again, lower rates are only a
response to weakness, not a cure for it.
And the UK, as we'll see, shows this
more clearly than maybe anywhere else.
Though, that list is starting to get a
little bit more crowded, as we'll also
see.
Politicians who want to actually succeed
should criticize and heavily, or even go
further, blame those who unleashed this
wave of decay and declared it a good
thing. Those who said it was going to
lead to widespread prosperity rather
than the near universal impoverishment
that it has. Farage would do well to
ditch the word affordability and start
speaking plainly, which is one of his
talents. The only economic words he
should ever say are jobs and incomes.
About why there wasn't nearly enough of
the latter and how increasingly,
increasingly, the former are being lost,
and I don't mean lost to the robots of
AI. The unemployment problem is hiding
right here in plain sight, even if no
one wants to talk about it. And as I
said, the UK is a perfect example of not
just the economic part of it, but also
the political response to it, the more
and increasingly extreme political
response to it.
What happens when political parties
refuse to be honest about the situation?
Well, the situation is problems in the
British job market showed up in 2024
even before the labor election
landslide. The economy's downfall isn't
due to one party or another one party
affiliation or another. It was the
lockdowns and the supply shock. And
before that, 2008 its aftermath, which
absolutely still haunts the world today.
Just ask China.
The UK began losing jobs right around
April and May 2024,
same as we've seen flat beverage show up
in the US or Canada and other parts of
the world. Rishi Sunak, the last Tory
Prime Minister, maybe the last Tory
Prime Minister, kept saying the British
economy was turning a corner. That's why
voters should vote for him.
And he was right, partly. It did turn a
corner, just the wrong one. And it ended
up being why voters voted so heavily
against him and his party. But while
labor promised to fix the economy, it
was their defining platform, by the way.
Don't forget this. Starmer made economic
reform his centerpiece and it backfired
bigly.
Not because labor focused on the
economy, but because they had no clue
why it was bad and certainly no idea it
was only going to get worse and
therefore no idea how to how to do
something about it. After all, they
thought they'd have the tailwind of
central bank rate cuts, but then the
rate cuts did them in Britain no favors
because rate cuts aren't stimulus. They
only tell you when central bankers are
reacting to weakness whether central
bankers say so in public or not. So jobs
that began being lost in summer 2024
kept being lost throughout 2025 and then
shockingly to the mainstream continued
to be lost here in 2026 just not in a
straight line. Every time it looks like
job growth is returning, they all
declare rate cut victory only to be
shocked when job losses come roaring
back after only a couple of months at
the most. And all the while, all the
while, unemployment keeps creeping
higher and higher and higher and higher
and higher. The official rate in Britain
had gotten to 5.2% as of January 2026,
which was a new cycle high and one that
wasn't far from the 2020 peak. Now
outside of lockdowns, it was the highest
jobless rate for the UK since the middle
2010s.
So unemployment and job losses are the
biggest problems in the UK, yet no one
will say it even as frustrated voters
continue to act on it. But it got worse
in February. The latest data from the
British government, even though the
unemployment rate slid from 5.2% to 4.9%
for anyone paying attention to the US
labor market or in Canada for the past 6
months, you already know why the rate
dropped and it is nothing good. Yeah,
it's what they call idleness in the UK.
Workers, now former workers, they see no
jobs out there, no one's hiring, more
people are firing and they simply give
up looking for work. They drop out of
the labor force, therefore they drop out
of the official jobless rate, even
though their joblessness is economic
nature and should be and really should
be reflected accurately in the major
numbers like those on unemployment.
But there are also those places unlike
the US such as Canada and now France
where even official unemployment rates
are getting to be too high to to at
least fully ignore as much as
politicians and central bankers might
want to. Despite the ECB, France's
jobless rate just moved up to 8.1% which
is as bad as it sounds.
And you might be asking yourself,
"Gee, when did French unemployment
really start to turn around and move
higher?" And the answer is, you'll not
be surprised to hear, the middle of
2024. Though most of the damage was done
in 2025 after the ECB had cut its policy
rates down substantially and kept going
right to 2% by the middle of last year.
And yet unemployment unexpectedly keeps
rising anyway. Quote, "French
unemployment unexpectedly rose to the
highest level in 5 years. 5 years.
Adding to signs the Euro area's second
largest economy was already on a weak
footing when the Iran war began. And
where have we heard this before? With
joblessness increasing across all age
categories, the rate reached 8.1% in the
first quarter, data from national
statistics agency INSEE showed.
Economists surveyed by Bloomberg had
forecast a slight decline, a slight
decline, to 7.8% from 7.9% at the end of
last year. And why did economists think
the unemployment rate would improve
early in 2026? Well, for one, they
thought weakness was all about trade
wars in 2025 rather than continuing the
impoverishment and the the consequences
of impoverishment from back in 2022.
Plus, let's not forget economists who
have no idea what interest rates are or
mean believe that their central bank
policy rate cuts, especially all the way
down to the 2% rate, right on the verge
of ultra low, those were going to be
huge, powerful support to the European
economy. That's what we're told all
across the media. That's what all the
textbooks say, and that's what history
shows is 100% completely wrong.
Christine Lagarde said Europe was in a
good place because of 2% yet here again
we see more evidence she was full of it.
Stop listening to central bankers. It
should be point number two for any
aspiring politician or political party.
And point number one is to simply be
honest about the economic situation,
including what is really going on and
where it came from, and thus stop
promising to fix what you really don't
know how to fix.
All they ever promised to do is keep
throwing government this and government
that at the economy when it has been
drowning in government since March and
April 2020. All that has done is
impoverished the vast majority of people
on the planet, and a good sizable part
of that majority does not like it. This
is really simple stuff. Prices went up
much farther than incomes did, and that
was in the early years of the decade up
until 2022 early 2023. Since then, it
has gotten worse because after not
having nearly enough incomes following
the lockdowns, hiring totally
disappeared, and increasingly jobs that
did exist are vanishing on top of
everything else. It really isn't that
hard to figure out why voters are so
pissed off, and why they are right to
be. The economy is and has been a total
show for years. Sure, the stock
market has boomed and central bankers
have declared it a good place. So what?
All those did was hide the truth. And
you do not have to take my word for
this. Take the increasingly radical
votes from voters who keep proving this
point. To the point that two of the
oldest parties in Europe have been
brought to the brink of extinction.
Rate of change in the economy goes down
and stays down. Rate of change in
politics goes way, way up.
And then there are the political
consequences from the energy shock and
the fallout from that, as well as what
that's going to do to the economy.
That's something that Mario and I talked
about in the video linked below. As
always, thank you very much for joining
me. Huge thank you. Euro Dollar
University members and subscribers. And
until next time,
take care.